He's in there?
他在里面吗？
He's not good now.
他现在不太好。
What's up, guys.
大家好。
I'm over there at the [] city, DJ [] is in there, it's not good,
我在[]城， DJ[]在那里，不太好，
whatever, he's behind on child support,
不管怎样，他在[孩子支持]后面，
so let's just go through this.
所以让我们先来看看这个，
So again the purpose of this lecture is,
所以，这门课的目的是，
we want to discuss the logistics for the course,
我们想要讨论课程的后勤，
now you know online rather than in person,
现在是在线的，而不是面对面的，
and so that way in the first day of class next week,
这样的话，下周第一天上课的时候，
we can just jump into all the daily stuff right away.
我们就可以直接跳到日常工作中去了。
All right, so let let's go through this.
好的，让我们来看看这个。
The reason again, why, why am I down here at the county [],
再说一遍为什么我会在县[监狱]，
well, because, because of databases, right,
这是因为数据库，
and this is what this course is really all about,
这就是这门课程的真正意义所在，
about we focusing on the like the most important things in your in your life
关于我们关注你生命中最重要的事情，
and yeah sometimes bad things happen,
是的，有时不好的事情会发生，
so for me, the the two most important things in my life,
所以对我来说，这是我生命中最重要的两件事，
are my wife and my biological daughter,
是我的妻子和我的亲生女儿，
first their number one, and then after that is databases,
首先是她们是第一的，然后是数据库，
that's really, you know what you should be getting out of this course,
那是你应该从这门课程中学到的，
the databases is all consuming,
数据库在消耗，
everything in the world, the database problem,
世界上的一切数据库的问题，
and you have think of a better appreciation for kind of stuff.
你已经想出了更好的欣赏这类东西的方法。
So again, we'll cover this in class next week.
所以，我们将在下周的课堂上讨论这一点。
All right, the another thing, important thing to point out for this lecture this semester this semester is,
好的，本学期这门课要指出的另一件重要的事情是，
we're griously sponsored by SingleStore
我们得到了 SingleStore 的大力赞助，
and they're helping out with with course development,
他们帮助我们进行课程开发，
so SingleStore is a in-memory column store distributed database system,
SingleStore 是一个内存中列存储分布式数据库系统，
that supports just in time, great compilation,
它支持即时、强大的编译，
now if none of that makes sense for you right now, that's, that's fine,
如果你现在觉得这些都不理解，也没问题，
because we cover all these things throughout semester,
因为我们整个学期都在讲这些东西，
and so we're grateful for them helping helping us out,
所以我们很感激他们帮助我们，
and they'll become giving a guest lecture at the at the end of the semester,
他们将在学期末的时候给我们做客座演讲，
some more that as we go along.
在我们前进的过程中，还有更多这样的东西。
Alright, so today's lecture real quickly,
好的，所以今天的课讲得很快，
we're just first obviously discuss the waitlist,
我们首先明确讨论等候名单，
that's what a lot of you guys care about,
这是你们很多人所关心的，
then we'll talk about the rules we have for lectures
然后我们将讨论课程的规则，
and then go through all the course logistics,
然后讨论所有课程的后勤工作，
including homework and projects.
包括家庭作业和项目。
So the first thing to obviously to deal with is the wait list,
所以，首先要处理的是等候名单，
as you're probably aware of, you're a senior student, the wait list is quite long,
如你所知，你是一名大四学生，等候名单相当长，
and you know, there's more people that can take want to take the course than we can actually accommodate,
想参加这门课程的人比我们实际能容纳的人多，
so at this point the, the CS department has taken over the wait list from from us,
所以，在这一点上， CS 系已经从我们手中接管了等待名单，
because they they need to make sure that certain students need to graduate
因为他们需要确保某些学生需要毕业，
and you know, take our source of collectives and all that
拿我们的集体来源和所有这些东西来说，
and they all get preference,
他们都有优先权，
so we the professors have no control over the wait list,
所以我们这些教授无法控制等待名单，
so if you send us emails there's there's not much, there's nothing we can we can do,
所以如果你给我们发邮件，我们就无能为力了，
and the admins will then move students off the wait list,
然后管理员会把学生从等待名单上移走，
but they're not always gonna go in the order that that you you're ranked in the wait list,
但他们不会总是按照你在等待名单中的排名顺序，
because multiple sections undergrad message,
因为多个部分都会导致信息不合格，
so just because you're some low on wait list,
所以不能因为你在等待名单上排名低，
there's no guarantee that we can get you in the semester,
不能保证我们能在这学期录取到你，
the good news is that,
好消息是，
since we've hired Jignesh Patel as the new data professor with me here at Carnegie Mellon,
由于我们聘请了 Jignesh Patel 作为卡内基梅隆大学的新数据教授，
we can now offer 15-445/645 every semester,
我们现在每学期可以提供 15-445/645 ，
so it'll be offered again in in Spring 2024 in addition to this semester.
所以，除了本学期外，它还将在 2024 年春季再次提供。
All right, so the other thing,
好的，另一件事，
when we have the in class lectures,
当我们在课堂上讲课时，
it's really important that,
很重要的一点是，
I wanted to be interactive,
我想要互动，
we don't just stand up there for, you know, an hour
我们不会只是站在那里一个小时，
and paddle on about databases,
然后在数据库上喋喋不休，
it's always helpful,
这总是有帮助的，
it's always fun, when students ask questions
当学生问问题时总是很有趣的，
and these questions be either because,
这些问题要么是因为，
we're talking too fast and he wants to slow down,
我们说得太快了，他想放慢语速，
I get excited when I talk about databases,
当我谈到数据库时，我会很兴奋，
so I'm going too fast, tell me to shut up and slow down,
所以我说得太快了，告诉我闭嘴，慢点说，
and certainly if you don't understand what we're talking about,
当然，如果你不明白我们在说什么，
it's a good time to interrupt,
这是一个很好的时间来打断我们，
to ask clarifying questions,
问一些澄清的问题，
because maybe there's something about, you know, in the slides or the discussion that that makes sense,
因为也许在幻灯片或讨论中有一些东西，这是有意义的，
and often times too, if you have questions,
通常情况下，如果你有问题，
other people have a have same questions as well,
其他人也会有同样的问题，
so please, anytime during the lectures,
所以请在课程期间的任何时间，
please interrupt us with anything that stated it's related,
请打断我们，说任何与此相关的事情，
what we don't want interrupted about is whether or not you can go to the bathroom,
我们不想被打扰的是你能不能上厕所，
because, you're an adult, you don't have to ask permissions,
因为，你是成人，不需要得到许可，
we also don't want be interrupted about blockchains,
我们也不想被区块链打断，
blockchain for databases are stupid,
数据库的区块链是愚蠢的，
we're not going to cover them, there's no need to cover,
我们不打算包括它们，没有必要包括，
we we're not covering these ends.
我们不会涉及这些方面的。
So now because I want you to interrupt us while we're giving the lectures,
现在，因为我想让你们在我们讲课的时候打断我们，
that means that we don't want you to come at the end of the end of the lecture and say,
这意味着我们不想让你们在课程结束时说，
oh, you know what about slide three, I did this didn't make sense it over, right,
你知道第三张幻灯片，我没有理解，
because in the past we we've always finished lectures,
因为在过去，我们总是完成讲座，
and you know, several students lined up asking the same question over and over again
几个学生排队一遍又一遍地问同样的问题，
and again, so that's why I'm saying,
所以我就是为什么我说，
if you interrupt us as we're going along,
如果你在我们进行的过程中打断我们，
you know, it help everyone at the same time,
这同时对每个人都有帮助，
so please, we won't answer any questions about the slides immediately after class.
所以，我们不会在下课后立即回答任何关于幻灯片的问题。
So what is this course,
那么，这是什么课程呢，
so 15-445/645 is a course about the design and implementation of of the database management systems,
所以， 15-445/645 是一门关于设计和实现数据库管理系统的课程，
now we we're going to discuss relational database management systems
我们将讨论关系数据库管理系统，
and we'll cover that in the next lecture,
我们将在下一节课中讨论这一点，
but it's really about how you should have to build these systems,
但这实际上是关于你如何构建这些系统的，
so this isn't, this isn't of course how to use one,
所以，这不是如何使用一个，
this isn't going how to put an application that that uses an ORM
这不是如何让一个应用使用 ORM ，
to make calls to the database or whatever,
来调用数据库等等，
is really how you build the internals of these systems.
而是如何构建这些系统内部的东西。
The reason why this you want to focus on this topic,
之所以要关注这个话题，
because no matter where you go in in your life,
因为无论你在生活的哪个方面，
in any aspect of computer science,
在计算机科学的任何方面，
where even outside of computer science,
甚至在计算机科学之外，
there'll be times, where you're always gonna be interacting with the database
你总是与数据库交互，
and therefore you need to know how these things are actually running,
所以你需要知道这些东西是如何运行的，
so if you don't go off and go to SingleStore
所以，如果你去 SingleStore ，
and work on actually the internal of the data system,
去研究数据系统的内部，
you need to know what's actually going on
你需要知道实际发生了什么，
to help you understand, you know, why the system behaving a certain way,
以帮助你理解为什么系统是某种行为，
I actually had people email me and tell me that,
实际上，人们给我发电子邮件，告诉我，
a lot of the concepts they databases are applicable to other things,
数据库中的许多概念适用于其他事情，
like queuing systems and what not,
比如排队系统等等，
so like, the things were coming this semester,
所以，这学期将要发生的事情，
I think will be super useful throughout your entire career.
我认为在你的整个职业生涯中都会非常有用。
So if you want to learn about how to use a database system
所以，如果你想学习如何使用数据库系统，
or how to administrate administer a database system, like being a DBA,
或如何管理数据库系统，比如成为一名 DBA ，
there's a couple courses in Heinz college that you should probably take instead,
Heinz 学院有几门课程你可能应该选择，
this is really about like people want to get their hands dirty on the internals of these systems.
这是关于人们想要对这些系统的内部结构动手。
All right, so the logistics of the course,
好的，所以课程的后勤，
everything will be on the course website,
一切都会在课程网站上，
we'll be publishing that very soon,
我们很快就会发布，
the all the discussions and announcements throughout the semester will be done through Piazza,
整个学期的所有讨论和公告都将通过 Piazza 完成，
all the homework and projects will be submitted through Gradescope,
所有的作业和项目都是通过 Gradescope 提交，
everything will be autograded,
一切都将自动打分，
and then the final grades will be posted on on Canvas,
然后最后的成绩将再次发布在 Canvas 上，
again if you're enrolled in the course,
如果你报名参加了这门课程，
officially, you should have access to all these things right now.
按照官方说法，你现在应该可以接触到所有这些东西。
So if you're a non-CMU student,
如果你不是 CMU 大学的学生，
because I know a lot of you outside,
因为我知道你们很多外面的人，
you like watch lectures and project,
你喜欢看讲座和项目，
well, we have a separate Gradescope account set up for the course,
我们为这门课程设立了一个单独的 Gradescope 账户，
that will mirror what the official CMU one does
它将镜像 CMU 官方所做的事情，
and you can use this code to to log in and and get access to it
你可以使用这个代码登录并访问它，
and this will allow you to submit your projects and get graded,
这将允许你提交你的项目，并获得评分，
the same way that the CMU students do,
就像 CMU 学生一样，
so again, if you're non-CMU student,
所以再说一次，如果你不是 CMU 学生，
we ask you since we're providing this, this materials for you for your charge,
我们为你提供了这个来为你评分，
please don't post your solutions on Github,
请不要把你的答案放在 Github ，
please don't email myself or Jignesh or TAs for help,
请不要给我或者 Jignesh 或助教发邮件寻求帮助，
we have so many people we need help here at CMU,
我们在 CMU 有太多的人需要帮助，
we can't help everyone,
我们不可能帮助所有人，
there is a Discord Channel that actually is not run by CMU,
有一个 Discord 频道不是由 CMU 运营的，
somebody outside of it has set this up,
它之外的某个人策划了这件事，
this sort of become the de facto location for discussing various aspects before,
这是以前讨论各种方面的实际位置，
so I encourage you to sign and check that out.
所以我鼓励你注册并查看。
And again, in in exchange for helping us out with this
再次，作为帮助我们的交换，
or you us helping everyone with these these materials,
或者帮助每个人这些材料，
I ask if someone please finish my Wikipedia article,
我请求谁来完成我的维基百科文章，
you know, there was some stuff that was sort of true, not true, whatever,
有些事情是真的，但不是真的，
someone could fix that for me, that would be great.
有人能帮我修好，那就太好了。
There's a textbook for the course,
有一本教科书，
database systems concepts from Silberschatz Korth Sudarshan,
来自 Silberschatz Korth Sudarshan 的数据库系统概念，
it's not required,
这不是必须的，
like there's no homework that are based on it,
没有基于它的作业，
but if you want supplemental reading beyond,
但如果你想要补充阅读以外的内容，
we discuss in the class you be reading,
我们会在课堂上讨论你正在阅读的内容，
you can go and dive deeper into various topics,
你可以深入探讨各种主题，
now there are gonna be some things that we discuss that the textbook doesn't cover,
现在我们要讨论一些课本上没有讲到的东西，
I don't covers as well as they should,
我没有讲到他们应有的，
and that's what we'll provide lecture notes as PDF files that are available there,
这就是我们将提供的课堂讲稿 PDF 文件，
whether you need to buy this textbook or not,
无论你是否需要购买这本教科书，
it's up to you,
由你决定，
it depends on how up you really want to go into this.
这取决于你想要进入这一领域的程度。
All right, so the grading rubric for this semester is me falling,
好的，这学期的评分题目是[这样的]，
so this is a project heavy course,
这是一门重工程的课程，
so the 45% of the grade will be based on your projects,
所以， 45% 的分数将基于你的项目，
and I discuss what these are in a second,
我马上就会讨论这些是什么，
the be five assignments, four projects, then a midterm exam and a final,
这是五个作业，四个项目，然后是期中考试和期末考试，
You see the breakdown here.
你可以看到这里的细目。
All right, so all the homework will be based on the material we cover in, in class and in the assign readings,
好的，所以所有的家庭作业都是基于我们在课堂上和指定阅读材料上所学到的材料，
the first homework assignment will be a SQL assignment or SQL project,
第一个家庭作业将是一个 SQL 作业或 SQL 项目，
where you write some SQL queries against the data set and see correct answer,
你将编写一些针对数据集的 SQL 查询，并看到所有问题的正确答案，
everything after that homework will be all pencil paper,
在那之后，家庭作业将全部是笔纸，
but you'll still see and code in and the autograded it there,
但你仍然会看到，代码自动评分，
again, it CMU everyone knows that,
再说一次，你们每个人都知道，
all your homework should be done individually and you shouldn't copy each other.
你们所有的家庭作业都应该独立完成，不应该互相抄袭。
All the projects will be based on a system we've been building for several years, called BusTub,
所有的项目都将基于我们在这里建造了几年的系统， BusTub ，
we discuss in the class, what the name actually means, came from,
在课程种，我们将讨论这个名字的含义，来自于什么，
but the idea here is that,
但这里的想法是，
it's a, it's educational test database system,
这是一个教育试验数据系统，
where you do all your projects
你在上面做所有的项目，
on and you'll see over time,
随着时间的推移，你会看到，
as you add more features to the system,
随着你给系统增加更多的功能，
you'll get a better understanding,
你会更好地理解如何，
how, how the, all the there layers fit together
所有这三个层可以放在一起，
and you can run queries and results based on stuff you actually go.
你可以根据你实际的东西来运行查询和结果。
So it's very important that you don't fall behind on the projects,
所以，重要的是不要在项目上落后，
because every project is going to build on the previous,
因为每个项目都将建立在先前项目的基础上，
like in project one, you're going to build a buffer manager,
比如在项目一中，你将构建一个缓冲区管理器，
then in project two, you're going to build an index,
然后，在项目二中，你将构建一个索引，
that that gets pages or gets gets empty,
获取页面或获取空类型，
so it's really important,
所以，这一点非常重要，
that you stay on track,
你要保持跟上，
start projects early and and don't fall behind.
尽早开始项目，不要落后，
BusTub is written in C++, I think 2017,
BusTub 是用 C++17 编写的，
we don't use all the advanced features,
我们没有使用所有先进特性，
but the,
但是，
the assumptions that you're coming into this class
假设你进入这门课的时候，
with the familiarity and and being comfortable with writing and debugging C++,
熟悉 C++ 的编写和调试，
and so I think it was a post on Piazza,
我认为在 Piazza 上的一个帖子，
whether 213 513 was, was enough of this,
213 513 是否足够了，
the answer's no,
答案是否定的，
some of the things you'll be able to pick up as you go along,
有些东西你可以边走边学，
but it's, it's a little I little more than 213.
但它比 213 多一点。
I'll cover later days in a second,
我会花点时间讲一下晚些时候，
but there,
但是，
well, the late days are only allowed for projects and the homework
好的，只有项目和家庭作业才允许晚些时候，
and you're given four late days, that you can use for any project,
你有四个晚些天的时间，你可以用来做任何项目，
as as we go along,
只要我们继续进行，
and as we release each project,
当我们发布每个项目时，
there'll be an online presentation,
会有一个在线演示文稿，
that will hold where you can come ask,
你可以来问，
you a week after the project released,
在项目发布一周后，
after you've sort of looked at the code,
在你看了代码之后，
you can come ask questions about it with the TAs
你可以通过助教来询问问题，
and before that make that available for everone.
在它发布给所有人之前。
So as posted in the, in the email,
所以，正如在电子邮件中发布的，
and I'll post that again,
我将再次发布，
there is a project zero,
有一个项目0，
that require all students that want to take the class have to complete,
要求所有想要选修这门课的学生必须完成，
and this is really a safety mechanism,
这实际上是一种安全机制，
to make sure that you're coming to this class prepared to write C++ code,
确保你来这门课的时候准备好写 C++ 代码，
and so it's not graded in that,
所以它不会评分，
it doesn't affect your final score in the class,
因为它不会影响你在这门课上的最终分数，
which you required to complete it,
你需要完成它，
because again, we don't want people who don't know C++,
因为，我们不想要不懂 C++ 的人，
I think they're gonna pick it up as they go along throughout the semester
我想他们会在整个学期学习的时候学起来，
and then realize,
然后意识到，
oh, I have to know C++ learn C++ and learn [] the same time,
我必须懂 C++ ，同时学习 C++ 和[]，
it, it does not end well,
它不会有好的结局，
trust me, we've done this up that,
相信我，我们已经做了这件事，
we realize that this really, really help you
我们意识到这真的帮助了你，
rather than make your life,
而不是改变了你的生活，
so if you do not complete this, this project zero by the deadline of september tenth,
所以，如果你不在 9 月 10 日的最后期限前完成这个项目0，
we're going to ask you to drop,
我们将要求你放弃，
and, and zero exceptions we made,
而且，没有任何例外，
I don't care that your brother took 513 ten years ago,
我不在乎你哥哥是不是十年前学了 513 ，
and you and you saw what he did back then,
你也看到了他当时的所作所为，
like, it doesn't matter,
这并不重要，
you have to complete this,
你必须完成这项工作，
it shouldn't take that much time, right,
它应该不会花那么多时间，
it's a pretty basic trial.
这是一个非常基本的试验。
For office hours,
对于办公时间，
the myself Jignesh and the TAs will hold office hours at various times throughout the week,
我和 Jignesh 和助教将在整个星期的不同时间，
but between Monday and Friday
但在周一到周五之间，
and then there won't be any office hours regularly on Saturdays,
周六将不会有任何常规的办公时间，
but the day before the every project is due,
但在每个项目到期的前一天，
we'll have that sort of power session,
我们将为你提供[电力]会议，
we have multiple for multiple hours available for you, ask questions for,
我们有多个助教多个小时来让你问问题，
but this means that there won't be any office hours on the Sunday,
但这意味着周日不会有任何办公时间，
when projects are due,
在项目到期之前，
because we don't want people wait to the last minute to try,
因为我们不想让人们等到最后一刻才尝试，
you know, to try to work on something
试图做某事，
and then, you know, hoping that TAs will help them figure things out right,
然后，希望助教能帮助他们解决问题，
Again, this is a forcing function to make sure that, you are making progress, you know, soon,
同样，这是一个强制功能，以确保你取得进展，
you start working projects as soon as they released,
你在项目一发布就开始工作，
you're not trying to do as much as you can at the last, last day,
你不会尽可能晚的去做，
system programming is not easy,
系统编程并不容易，
and you will make mistakes and you have time to figure out.
你会犯错，你有时间弄清楚。
For this semester, we're actually offering the course to, to CMU-Q students,
在本学期，我们为 CMU-Q 学生开设这门课程，
so welcome, thank you joining us,
谢谢加入我们，
and I realize there's timezone difference
我意识到这里有时差，
and so we will have A A regularly scheduled office hour,
所以，我们将有一个定期安排的办公时间，
that lines up with your you your working hours,
与你的工作时间相一致，
with a different TA each week,
每周有不同的助教，
I'll announce this Piazza,
我会发布在 Piazza 上，
when will be, that we these to,
当我们准备好，
talk to somebody if you need to
如果你需要和某人交谈，
and then if you need to talk to myself,
然后如果你需要和我交谈，
it will post how to schedule calls us at different times as needed,
它会发布如何根据需要在不同的时间安排[]给我们，
again, so this this morning session, or it will be, will be for the CMU-Q students,
再次，这个上午的时间是为 CMU-Q 学生开设的，
we ask the regular, the Pittsburgh CMU students not to use that,
我们要求普通的匹兹堡的 CMU 学生不要使用它，
and by all means, please always questions post on Piazza,
当然，请务必把问题贴在 Piazza 上，
we'll answer it sooner.
我们将尽快回答。
I guess, delay policy for homework,
我想对于家庭作业的延迟策略，
to lose 10% every 24 hour is late
每晚 24 小时减 10% ，
and then before they I'm talking about will be only be applicable to for projects,
然后在我说之前说的，只适用于项目，
if there's a medical emergency,
如果有医疗紧急情况，
if there's some kind of the term medical emergency,
如果有某种医疗紧急情况，
if you need an extension email as soon as possible
你需要尽快发送一封延期电子邮件，
and that way we make sure we make the appropriate necessary you to go medical thing the,
这样我们就会确保我们为你提供适当的必要医疗服务，
but emails sooner rather than later,
但电子邮件越早越好，
it's not ten years, ten weaks,
不要是十年，十周，
and you come here to help. Let us know,
你请求帮助，让我们知道，
All right, I got say every year, do not plagiarize,
好的，我每年都要说，不要抄袭，
so all the homework, all the projects must be your own original work,
所有的家庭作业，所有的项目都必须是你自己的原创工作，
are not group assignments,
不是小组作业，
you can discuss your projects with students, that's fine,
你可以和学生讨论你的项目，那很好，
you can mean flesh out ideas on the whiteboard,
你可以在白板上充实想法，
but do not copy source code from other people,
但不要抄袭他人的源代码，
do not copy source code from Github,
不要复制 GitHub 的源代码，
so again, because we make this public to people outside CMU,
再说一次，因为我们向 CMU 以外的人公开了这个，
there's a lot of implementations from previous semesters from that are available on Github,
在 GitHub 上有很多前一个学期的实现，
Chatgpt might be able to even do earlier projects,
Chatgpt 甚至可以做更早的项目，
do not copy them,
不要复制它们，
because we the we use Gradescope now
因为现在使用 Gradescope ，
and Gradescope has a [] checker
Gradescope 有一个[]检查器，
and basically what we do is,
我们要做的是，
we find all the Github implementations from non-CMU students,
我们从非 CMU 学生那里找到所有 GitHub 的实现，
load them up into Github, into Gradescope but fake students
将它们加载到 GitHub 中， Gradescope 中，然后假的学生，
and then see whether you match against them,
然后看看你是否与他们匹配，
do not, do not copy your source code from other students,
不要从其他学生那里抄袭代码，
do not copy source code from Github,
不要使用 GitHub 的源代码，
the Github source code is usually pretty crappy,
GitHub 的源代码通常非常糟糕，
we've done experience before she has done this,
在她做这件事之前，我们已经有过经验，
the CMU students crush the non-CMU students,
CMU 的学生压倒了非 CMU 的学生，
so it's actually in your best interest not to copy now.
所以现在不抄袭是为了你们的最大利益。
Again, there won't be any exceptions, oh, I didn't know,
再次，不会有任何例外，我不知道，
yeah, the fact that this is recorded lecture,
这是录像的课程，
if we have to report you to Warner hall,
如果我们必须向华纳音乐厅举报你，
we point to this timestamp in in the lecture and say
我们指着讲座中的时间戳说，
where I'm warning you enough to plagiarize
我警告你抄袭，
and then you plagiarize. Yeah, and if not, you're screwed, right,
然后你抄袭了，是的，你就完了，
if there's something you want to do that seems kind of like grey zone
如果你想做的事情看起来像是灰色地带，
and you don't know if it's okay,
你不知道，是否可以，
like using Chatgpt or something like that, right,
使用 Chatgpt 或类似的东西，
please, you know, email myself and Jignesh not the TAs
请发邮件给我和 Jignesh ，而不是助教，
to see whether you know, and see whether we want to discuss it,
看看看看我们是否想讨论这个问题，
and then the link there would be CMU's policy or academic integrity,
然后，这里的链接是 CMU 的学术诚信政策，
again, we take this very seriously, don't around.
再说一次，我们非常认真地对待这件事，不要越界。
All right, one of the last thing is that,
好的，最后一件事是，
if you love as much as I do
如果你像我一样热爱，
and you go beyond the course material,
而且你超越了课程材料的范围，
we are offering a seminar series this semester,
我们本学期将提供一个系列研讨会，
it's entirely optional,
这完全是可选的，
where every Monday starting in September,
从 9 月份开始的每个星期一，
we having a different outside speaker come
我们都有一个不同的外部演讲者，
give a talk about the various database company or project,
来做关于各种数据公司或项目的演讲，
so this semester of the theme is machine learning for databases and databaseases machine learning,
本学期的主题是针对数据库的机器学习和数据库机器学习，
and so we have people that are building a lot of these hot thing now,
所以我们现在有很多人正在构建很多热门的东西，
these vector databases,
这些矢量数据库，
but discuss next class,
但我们讨论下一节课，
but we're having them talked about their systems,
但我们让他们谈论他们的系统，
how to support ML like stuff inside of data systems,
如何在数据系统中支持 ML 之类的东西，
and then we'll have people talk about how they're using machine learning to optimize data systems,
然后我们会让人们谈论他们是如何使用机器学习来优化数据系统的，
sort of like using to make the system actually faster,
比如用来使系统更快，
so again this is optional,
再次，这是可选的，
everything will be on Zoom on Monday at four thirty
每周一四点半在 Zoom 上，
and then they will post it on Youtube afterwardswards,
然后他们会再次把它发布到 YouTube 上，
again, in this one, you don't have to be a senior,
在这个项目中，你不一定非得是大四学生，
neither you can join it, if you you can see the list of the full schedule.
你可以参加，如果你看到全部的计划表。
Alright, so that's it for the legislative class,
好的，这就是后勤课程，
I gotta figure out what about,
我得弄清楚是关于什么的，
he's not getting now, anytime soon,
他在短期内不会变成现在这样，
that's about, but it's okay.
差不多了，不过没关系。
So next class on Monday,
所以，周一的下一节课，
we'll have the in class lecture
我们将进行课堂讲课，
and then we'll begin right out of the gate,
然后我们就走出大门，
not talking any logistics, but the course,
不是说任何后勤，而是课程，
we'll just immediately talk about the relational model and databases.
我们将直接讨论关系型模型和数据库。
All right, guys, see you next week.
好的，大家，我们下周见。